Hello everyone.
大家好
I'm Cheng Jiayang, uh...
我是程家阳呃
So today, I'll be presenting some of our recent work.
今天要报告的是我们的一个最近的工作
MMGM.
M m jm
This is a framework designed for, um, long conversation scenarios.
这是一个针对长对话场景中嗯
an interactive evaluation framework for AI assistant memory, uh...
AI助手记忆的一个交互式的评估框框架呃
Today's presentation will be divided into four parts.
今天的内容分为四个部分
First, let's talk about the motivation.
首先是motivation部分啊
In this section, we will introduce... uh...
这里我们会介绍呃
So, why is memory evaluation such an important topic?
为什么记忆评估是一个比较重要的话题
as well as some of the shortcomings in existing work.
以及现有工作的一些短板
The second part is the framework of MMGM.
第二部分是m m gm的framework
And then, uh, we'll move on to...
然后接着我们会呃
Let's talk about this interactive evaluation framework.
讲下基于这个交互式的评估框架
So, with MMGM, our experiments revealed that...
MMGM我们的实验发现啊
Finally, let's go over some key takeaways.
最后是一些key takeaways
So, why is memory evaluation such an important area of research?
嗯为什么记忆评估是一个重要的方向呢
So, let's paint a picture here.
啊我们可以设想一个场景啊
Nowadays, pretty much everyone uses an AI assistant.
现在大家都会使用AI助手
Imagine you're having a conversation with an AI assistant for, say, 500 turns.
想象你跟一个AI助手聊天聊了500轮呃
Let's say you mentioned something about yourself back in the third round.
你在第三轮的时候提到了自己
or say, a food allergy, after hundreds of turns in the conversation.
比如说食物过敏几百轮之后
does it still remember that key piece of information?
他是不是还记得这个关键的信息
So, this is actually about, uh...
这个其实是对呃
is a very critical dimension of the user experience in agent interaction.
agent的交互的用户体验一个非常关键的维度
In other words, an agent needs to, throughout a long-term interaction,
也就是说A证的需要在长期交互中
to consistently maintain accurate information.
持续维持一个准确的信息
And if the memory fails,
并且一旦记忆出错
users will run into inconsistencies,
用户就会遇到前后矛盾
and keep asking questions like these.
反复提问这一类的问题
and ultimately, lose all trust in the agent.
最终失去对于agent的一个信任
Mmm, and this is especially true for personal assistants and customer service.
嗯这点在personal assistant客服
And other dimensions, like collaborative coding, for instance.
还有一些比如说collaborative coding这些维度
In these scenarios, this is actually a critical issue.
这些场景中其实都是非常关键的
Mmm, but the question is, how should we properly evaluate this?
嗯但是问题是我们应该怎么去正确的评估
An ability like this,
这样一个能力
existing memory evaluation frameworks
现有的记忆评估的框架
these memory benchmarks,
这些memory benchmark啊
Take MSC, for example.
比如说MSC啊
or LOCOMO,
LOCOMO啊
They all rely on a static, off-policy evaluation dataset.
他们都依赖于一个静态的of policy的评估数据啊
The problem with this is that...
这样的一个问题是
The thing is, they just can't capture the kind of...
他们其实没有办法去捕捉真实对话中的
interactive and ever-evolving characteristics.
交互式的和不断演变的一些啊特性
...these characteristics of how information flows, you see.
信息流动的这样的一些特性嗯
In a real-world deployment,
在真实的部署中
the agent's own evaluation, uh,
agent自己的评估呃
its own responses will feed back into the conversation,
自己的回复是会参与到对话的
and in shaping the context.
上下文的塑造中的
But traditional evaluations, this kind of static, off-policy assessment,
而传统的评测这一类静态的of policy的评估啊
It completely ignores this interactive aspect.
它是完全忽略了这种啊交互式的
this coupled relationship.
这种耦合的关系
And this, in turn, leads to memory evaluations...
这也就导致记忆的评估啊
in essence, it's an evaluation result that deviates from real-world scenarios.
其实是一个偏离真实场景的评估结果
We can use this table to compare them.
我们可以用这张表来对比
So, to elaborate on this... uh...
具体说明这个情况呃
All the previous benchmarks share two key, fundamental flaws.
之前的所有benchmark都有两个共同的关键缺陷
First of all, they all use a static, off-policy evaluation.
首先他们都使用一个静态的of policy的评估啊
So, by 'static off-policy,' we mean the agent is given a piece of text to read through,
这里的静态of policy指的是agent会去读一段
a pre-written conversation.
预先写好的conversation
and then answer questions based on that static conversation.
基于这个静态的对话内容去回答问题
So, what this is actually testing is the entire...
这实际上测的其实是A整
reading comprehension of a given dialogue.
对于一段对话内容的阅读理解
rather than a truly dynamic, interactive process, you know, as we'd normally think of it.
而不是一个呃真正我们理解上的动态交互式的
the ability to evaluate memory.
记忆的评估的能力
And the second point is...
第二点就是啊
None of these evaluation frameworks provide feedback for optimization.
这些评估框架都不提供一个优化方面的反反馈
what we call 'optimization feedback'.
我们这里叫optimization feedback
In other words, uh, it can tell you what score the model got.
也就是说呃他可以反馈模型的得分多少
Let's say it gets a score of 60.
比如说得了60分
But the problem is, we don't know why.
但是我们却不知道啊
But behind that score,
在这个得分背后
what exactly are the model's problem areas,
模型到底在哪些方面出了问题
and how to make targeted improvements to these problem areas.
并且怎么去针对这些出问题的方面去做改进
Uh...
呃
In our work,
在我们的工作中
So, in our work, MMGM...
在我们的工作MMGM中啊
And we've managed to tackle the issues in both of these dimensions at the same time.
我们同时解决了这两个维度的问题
First, we switched the evaluation mode to a, uh...
首先我们是把evaluation mode切换到了一个呃
an interactive and dynamic evaluation, uh...
交互式的动态的一个评估呃
um, under this framework, uh...
呃框架下呃
The second point is about the optimization feedback.
第二点的话就是针对optimization feedback
We've provided a series of diagnostic tools.
我们去提供了一系列的诊断工具
So, in addition to the traditional overall metrics,
就是在传统的overall the matrix之外
We also provide a set of diagnostic metrics.
我们还会提供一些diagnostic metric啊
So, based on these diagnostic metrics, developers...
基于这些diagnostic metric开发者
And there's more.
还有这些啊
the agent's developers can make targeted improvements.
agent的这个研发人员是可以去针对性的改进
the corresponding framework.
对应的框架啊
And our framework has some other features as well.
并且我们的框架还有一些其他的特性
For instance, it allows for configurable dialogue lengths.
比如说啊可以去啊有有可配置的对话长度
So, in theory, it can be extended to cover pretty long conversations.
理论上可以extend到比较长的对话范围啊
And it also takes diversity into account.
并且还会有一些diversity方面的考虑
You can find the corresponding details in the original paper.
这个可以在原文中去看到对应的细节呃
Let's use a concrete example to illustrate this.
我们可以用一个具体的例子来说明啊
So, for instance, uh, let's consider a scenario where a user is talking to an assistant.
比方说呃在一个用户和assistant对话的场景中
So, the user mentions that...
这用户提到啊
I switched from doing yoga to swimming last month.
我上个月从练瑜伽切换成了游泳
Under the current methods used in existing work,
在现有的工作的做法下
So, under this kind of off-policy evaluation framework,
就是这种of policy的评测框架下
All agents are reading from the exact same pre-written dialogue.
所有的agent读的都是完全相同的预写对话
In other words,
也就是说
So, if we're evaluating two different agents, say Agent A and Agent B,
我们如果评测agent a和agent b这两个不同的agent
So, the context they're actually seeing is exactly the same.
他们其实看到的上下文是一模一样的啊
And that's exactly why I was saying...
这也就是为什么刚刚说
Essentially, you're just testing the agent's reading comprehension,
本质上只是在测agent的阅读理解
rather than its actual memory capabilities.
而不是真正的memory memory能力
or, in other words, its memory capabilities.
或者说记忆能力
Uh, now let's look at our on-policy setting.
呃现在来看我们的on policy设定
So, A in AWE remembered that the user likes, uh...
AH的A记住了用户喜欢用户呃
Oh, sorry, the user likes sports.
sorry用户喜欢运动
So it naturally replied, 'Okay.'
所以很自然的回复好的
I've switched to swimming now.
我换成游泳了
But Agent B completely forgot what was said before.
但是agent的B完全忘记了之前的内容啊
This might be, uh, due to some flaws in the design of its memory mechanism.
可能是呃由于他的某些记忆机制设计上的缺陷
So, it forgot the information from before.
他忘记了之前这条信息啊
and instead asks, "So, what kind of sports have you been playing?"
转而提问你之前有在做什么运动吗
So, these kinds of differences in memory mechanism design...
啊这样的一个记忆机制设计方面的不同
And that's going to lead to a completely different trajectory for the conversation.
就会导致完全不同的对话轨迹啊
So, here's the key takeaway.
所以说关键点就在于啊
The design of the memory system affects the agent's response,
记忆的设计会影响agent的回复
And in turn, these responses shape the entire trajectory of the conversation.
而回复又塑造了整个对话的走向
And the evaluation of memory is, in fact, coupled with the direction of the entire conversation.
而记忆的评测和整个对话走向其实是耦合的
The traditional, uh, evaluation frameworks...
传统的呃评测框架
This kind of off-policy evaluation framework, however, actually breaks this coupling.
这种of policy的评测框架其实是打破了这种耦合
This, in turn, leads to an unrealistic evaluation result.
也就带来了一个不真实的评测结果
This diagram summarizes the differences between the two.
这张图总结了两者的区别啊
On the left, we have the 'of policy' method.
左边是of policy
The agent will read a fixed piece of dialogue.
agent会读一段固定的对话啊
and then generate answers to questions.
并且生成回答问题啊
and answer questions.
回答问题啊
The agent being evaluated has never actually participated in this conversation.
被评测的agent其实从未真正的参与过这段对话
And on the right, we have the on-policy method.
而右边是on policy
This means the agent is participating in the conversation in real-time.
就是agent的实时参与对话
and generates its own replies.
生成自己的回复啊
Next, we test its... uh... its own...
接着我们去测试他与他对自己呃
and its ability to remember the content from this exchange.
参与的这段交换交互内容的一个记忆能力啊
And this 'on-policy' approach on the right,
这右边这种on policy
In fact, it also reflects a condition of real-world deployment.
其实还反映了真实部署的一个条件
So, in other words,
也就是说啊
The agent's own response becomes part of the context.
agent他自己的回复会成为上下文的一部分
So, this is the overall framework of MMGM.
嗯这是MMGM的整体框架啊
This diagram might be a little small.
这个图可能有点小
You can check out our project website for more details.
大家可以去看我们的project website
or, you can check out the full paper itself.
或者说我们的论文原文
So, overall, this is a three-stage process.
总体来说这是一个三阶段的啊
pipeline.
Pipeline
In the first stage, we'll generate some structured data.
第一阶段我们会去生成一个结构化的数据啊
based on a, uh, predefined state schema.
基于一个呃提前给定好的状态的schema
to simulate the evolution of the state.
去做状态演化啊
In the second stage,
在第二阶段
In other words, on-policy interaction.
也就是说on policy interaction啊
the agent will interact with an in-framework user simulator,
agent会和一个框架内的用户模拟器
to engage in a real conversation with the user simulator.
user simulator进行真实的对话
And in the third stage,
在第三阶段啊
We will then take the collected on-policy compositional traces,
我们会对采集好的这种on policy的composition trace
to conduct...
去做啊
a series of fine-grained evaluations.
一个一系列的细粒度的评估呃
And at each of these multiple checkpoints, we use personalized Q&A.
并且在每个多个check point处去通过个性化的QA啊
to evaluate the memory capabilities of the model or the agent.
评估模型的或者agent的记忆能能力
Alright, let's dive into the details of data generation.
呃我们来详细说一下数据生成
We define this as the entity schema.
我们定义这个energy schema
This includes both attributes and relationships.
包含啊attributes和relationships
And these states will continuously evolve as the conversation progresses.
这些状态会随着啊对话推进不断演化
For example, they can be updated, added, or deleted.
比如说有更新或者说新增或者说删除嗯
So, in period one, uh...
在period1的时候呃
The age range of the participants is mostly in their fifties.
参加者年龄范围是mostly fifty bus
And by period three, it's changed to...
到了period three就变成了啊
mixed the ages with young adults.
Mixed the ages with young adults
Uh...
呃
So, in these conversations,
这些对话啊
These changes in information
这些信息的变化
In fact, this is a very common phenomenon that happens during conversations.
其实是在谈话过程中非常常见的一个现象啊
And that's why we use a schema-based approach like this.
也是为什么我们用这样一个ska base啊
to reflect this phenomenon through state evolution.
state evolution去反映这种现象
And the agent, in fact, must be able to accurately track these changes.
而agent的其实是必须需要去准确追踪这些变化啊
so that it can answer the questions in our subsequent evaluation.
才能回答我们后续的评估方面的问题
So, why design it this way?
为什么要这样设计呢
Well, the first is this schema-based method.
嗯首先是这种chema base的方法
It's, uh, highly controllable.
它是呃有比较好的可控性
In other words, there's a precise ground truth at every single point in time.
也就是说每个时间点都有精确的ground
truth.
truth啊
The second point is authenticity.
第二点就是真实性
So, this scenario can actually be designed to be...
这个场景其实可以设计为
an information flow that's quite close to a real conversation.
跟真实对话比较贴近的信息流啊
And the last point is scalability.
最后一点是SCALABILITY
In other words, the length of the dialogue can be extended indefinitely.
也就是说啊这个对话的长度是可以任意扩展的
Uh, so, in the interaction phase, uh...
呃那么在交互阶段呃
A user simulator is then used to gradually...
U1个user simulator就被用来逐步的在啊
to convey this kind of information we just mentioned throughout our multi-turn conversations.
我们的多轮对话中传递刚刚提到的这种啊
the information about state evolution, um.
state evolution的信息嗯
at a predefined checkpoint.
在设定好的checkpoint处
We'll then inject a memory query to test its recall of that specific information.
我们会注入啊memory query去测试对应的信息
point.
点
The agent needs to retrieve from the dialogue history it has participated in,
agent的需要从自己参与过的对话历史中
to recall this information.
去回忆这些内容
and answer questions.
并且回答问题呃
Now, in terms of evaluation,
评估方面的话
We provide, uh, both the end-to-end QA accuracy,
我们既提供呃端到端的q a accuracy
as an overall score.
作为一个overall score啊
In addition, we also provide some scores related to memory capabilities.
除此之外也会提供一些记忆能力相关的score
This score is, uh, based on the overall score.
这个score是在呃基于overall score
we performed a normalization.
做了一个normalization
So, we're starting with a random baseline.
就是我们在一个随机的baseline啊
and a baseline calculated from the upper bound of memory capacity with a perfect memory.
和一个perfect memory的上届的一个记忆能力的BAS算
and devised a plan within that framework.
之中去做了一个规划
to decouple the memory ability from the reasoning ability.
把memory的能力从啊reasoning的能力中解耦合出来
to get a more realistic score for its memory performance, uh...
做一个啊更真实的一个记忆方面的得分呃
And last but not least, a crucial point is that...
最后一个更重要的一点是
We provide a set of diagnostic metrics.
我们提供一套诊断性的指标啊
In other words, a diagnostic matrix.
也就是diagnostic matrix
Here, we provide a breakdown across three stages.
这里我们提供三个阶段的分解啊
namely, memory writing, reading, and utilization.
也就是记忆的写入读取以及利用呃
So, for these three stages,
在针对这三个阶段的啊
we've broken down the agent's failure rate.
agent的失败率去做了一个分解
This allows us to precisely pinpoint the agent's memory capabilities.
我们就可以去啊精确的定位agent的记忆能力
So, where exactly does the problem lie? Hmm.
到底在哪个环节出现了问题嗯
Okay, so let's move on to the experimental results.
OK啊接下来就看一下实验结果部分啊
Alright, so the first question is about our...
首先第一个问题是涉及到我们的啊
So, what's the main purpose of this entire framework?
整个框架的定位哎
So, the question is, can off-policy evaluation really be misleading?
就是of policy evaluation真的会带来一个误导吗
On the left, we have the different...
左边是不同的啊
Alright, let's look at the comparison of memory agent configurations.
memory agent配置的对比啊
Here, you can see the change in the ranking.
这里可以看到rank的变化
So, these are the scores for on-policy and off-policy.
就是呃on policy和of policy的得分
In fact, there's a clear difference in the rankings.
其实在啊rank上是有一个明显的不同的
For example, AWE, which stands for, uh, Agent's Write to External memory.
比如说啊AWE也就是呃agented write a agent entic right啊
Right to external memory.
Right to external memory
So, writing is, uh, this kind of thing.
写写就是这种呃
The agent autonomously decides what information
agent自主决定把什么信息
and write it to an external storage.
写入到外部的一个存储中
So, this is the baseline, uh...
这样一个BASSLINE呃
Under the on-policy setting, it actually ranked first.
他在on policy下面其实是排第一位的
But under the off-policy setting, it dropped to third place.
但是它在of policy下啊下下降掉了第三名
This could be because, in the off-policy phase,
这可能是由于of policy阶段啊
we don't actually allow it to.
我们其实并不允许啊
for the agent to generate a response that is consistent with its own memory content.
agent去做一个符合他自身记忆内容的回复
So this, uh, this kind of limits the agent's performance.
所以这个限制了这个agent的一些嗯一些发挥
The table on the right shows the results for the native LM.
右边这张表是native lm
This is a result from the native large model.
native大模型的一个结果啊
The rankings here are relatively stable.
这里的排名相对是还比较稳定的
But there are still some subtle differences.
但是也会有一些啊细微的差异
So, we can see from these two results that...
嗯这个从这两个结果中可以看出来
This is what we call an off-policy evaluation.
就是of policy的评估
This introduces what's called a 'reuse bias'.
它会引入一个reuse bias啊
So, when you're trying to optimize your... uh...
这个在你试图去优化你的啊
memory agent or memory system,
memory agent或者memory system的时候
can actually be detrimental.
是有其有害的啊
On the other hand, for a native large model,
反而对于一个原生的大模型
For example, when it comes to evaluating long-form text,
你比如说做长文本的评估来说
Perhaps the drawbacks of off-policy methods aren't that obvious, huh?
可能of policy它的劣势并不是那么明显啊
As for the agent side,
在在agent的方面
This is a design that is quite obviously detrimental.
这个是一个比较明显有害的设计
So, the second question is...
那第二个问题是
So, what about the current large models?
当前的大模型
So, how good is their memory really in long conversations?
在长对话中记忆能力到底怎么样啊
We've provided heatmaps for two matrices.
我们提供了两个matrix的热力图
One is the overall score.
一个是啊总体的得分
and the other is the normalized memory score.
一个是啊经过归一化之后的记忆得分
If we just focus on the memory score, um, we'll find that...
我们可以只看记忆得分这一块嗯会发现
And we made two key discoveries.
有两个关键发现啊
The first point is that as the conversation gets longer,
第一点是随着对话变长啊
Now, the horizontal axis for both of these heatmaps...
这两个热力图的横轴都是啊
the different periods of the conversation,
对话的不同的这个period
For example, from period zero to period ten.
比如从第零个period到第十个period
indicating different turns in the conversation, from light to dark, uh...
反应对话中不同的轮次由浅到深呃
As the conversation gets longer,
随着对话变长
we'll find that the model and the agent... uh...
我们会发现模型和agent的啊
Sorry.
抱歉
And it's only when we test the models that we see their performance plummet.
这也是只有测模型模型的性能是急剧下降的
For most models, in the middle to later stages of the conversation,
大多数模型在中后期的period中
Its performance dropped to below 50% of its initial capability.
就掉到了他上舰能力的啊50%以下啊
Sometimes, it even drops below the random score.
甚至有时候会低于random school
Second, the memory score is significantly lower than the 'abroad' score.
第二点是记忆得分是远低于abroad的得分
In other words, as you can see in the chart, the score for the one on the right is lower than the one on the left.
也就是右边这个图他的得分是要低于左边
And this is also pretty intuitive.
这个这个也是比较intuitive
This is quite intuitive.
比较直观的
Because that just reflects the model's surface-level fluency in its responses.
因为啊意味着表面的模型的一些回答的流畅性
This actually masks the failure of its underlying memory mechanism.
其实掩盖了它底层的记忆机制的失败
So, the model might sound very confident,
就说模型听起来很自信
But in reality, it's already forgotten some key information.
但是其实已经忘了一些关键的信息
Alright, so the third question we're interested in is...
嗯第三个问题我们关心的是嗯
So, can the external memory mechanism actually help?
external memory机制到底能不能帮上忙啊
And by 'external memory', we mean something that exists outside of the model itself.
这里external memory指的是在模型之外
We hooked up some external frameworks to assist the model.
我们外挂了一些框架去辅助模型
used to store memory information.
用于存储记忆信息
We tested three different implementations.
我们测了三种实现
Right, and you can see this implementation in the diagram on the right.
嗯嗯这个实现在右边这张图里面可以看出来
The first is the traditional RAG.
一个是传统的RAG
In other words, we store the entire conversation history.
也就是说我们存储完整的对话历史
into an external vector store.
到一个外部的vector store里边
and retrieves the relevant information when answering questions.
并且在回答问题的时候去检索对应的信息
to use as context.
作为context啊
And then there's also AWE.
另外还有就是AWE啊
Agent-based External Memory.
agent tic memory external啊
This means we let the agent decide for itself what information...
这个是说我们让agent自主决定什么信息
what to store and what not to store.
该存什么不存
and let it decide autonomously what gets stored in an external memory bank. Okay,
让他自主决定什么会存到一个外部的memory bank好
And there's another type, which is AWI.
另外还有一种一种是AWI
That's right. It's the energetic memory in context.
就是啊ergetic memory in in context
This part is somewhat similar to AWE.
这里的话跟aw有点类似
The difference is that...
区别在于
It just compresses the information into the large model's context.
它只把信息压缩到大模型的一个context
into the buffer, um...
buffer里边嗯
So, we've made a few discoveries here.
这里我们有几个发现啊
First off, the AWE approach delivered the best performance.
首先是啊AWE的这种啊表现是最好的
This means letting the model autonomously decide what information to filter and remember.
是让模型自主决定筛选要去记住什么信息
This is more efficient than just storing everything.
比直接存所有东西更高效
The second finding is that, uh, while RAG is very simple,
第二个发现是呃RAG虽然很简单
not selective enough, hmm.
不够精选嗯
Uh, but... but it's not selective enough.
呃但但但是不够啊精选
So that's what leads to this, uh...
所以说导致这个啊
the results of retrieval are quite noisy.
retrial或者是检索的结果比较noisy
And this would lead to, uh, a... a... compared to AWE,
这个就会带来相对于a we的一个啊啊
a lower score, uh...
一个更低的得分呃
What was surprising, though, was that...
出乎意料的一个点是
We found that the implementation of this memory mechanism, AWI...
我们发现AWI这种记忆机制的实现啊
In other words, the model takes this memory content
也就是说把模型把这个记忆内容
writes it into its own context.
写到他的一个自身的context里面啊
And in our tests, this strategy...
这种策略在我们测试中
It might even perform worse than the native one,
它会甚至比原生的啊
The performance of large models actually gets worse with long contexts.
长上下文的大模型表现要更差啊
This could mean compressing information into a buffer,
这可能意味着把信息压缩到buffer里边
it might actually lose some key details,
可能反而会丢失一些关键细节比啊
It might even be more harmful than not compressing the information at all.
甚至比不去做这样的压缩更有害
And finally, we looked into the reasons why the models failed.
啊最后是我们对啊模型失败的原因
and conducted a series of diagnostic analyses.
去做了一些一系列的诊断性的分析
Let's break it down into a few dimensions.
我们分几个维度来看
First, let's look at the strategy dimension.
首先是strategy维度呃
As we just saw, there's also AGENTIC RISE.
我们刚刚也看到就是啊agetic rise
Its overall score is pretty good.
它整体的得分比较好啊
Through a more detailed diagnostic analysis,
经过更细一步的诊断分析
We found that it actually did improve...
我们发现它其实是提升了啊
its ability to actually utilize the information it has stored.
记忆内容的一个利用的这个方面的能力啊
But the trade-off is that it sacrifices some of its read performance.
但是代价是他牺牲了一些读取的性能啊
This could be because, uh, in the compressed information...
这可能是因为它在呃压缩的信
during the process of compressing information into this external knowledge base.
压缩信息进入这个外部的知识库的过程中啊
This compression process results in information loss.
这个压缩过程造成了信息的丢失
The second dimension is the update frequency.
第二个维度是update frequency
And here, we found that...
嗯这里我们发现啊
The lower the frequency at which the agent writes to its memory,
agent他的记忆写入的这个频率越低
The lower this update frequency is,
这个更新频率越低
the higher its read failure rate becomes.
它的读取的失败率越高啊
This could be because it's retaining too many local messages.
这可能是因为保留过多的local message
This can cause some confusion.
会造成一定的混淆
Uh, also, there are some other factors like noise and top-k.
嗯此外还有一些啊noise跟top k之类的
I won't go into too much detail on that.
这个我就不继续展开了啊
So, these diagnostic metrics allow us to do a few things.
这些诊断性的指标可以让我们去做一些啊
and make targeted optimizations.
有指向性的优化啊
for the memory design of our agent.
针对我们的agent的记忆设计
rather than just blindly trial-and-erroring.
而不是说去盲目的试错
or making blind improvements.
盲目的改进
Ah, this chart here is also a table.
啊这这张图也是一个额表格
So, this is about those diagnostic metrics we just mentioned.
就是刚刚提到的几种诊断性的指标的一个啊
Explanation.
解释
Uh, and we also found that, uh, if we look at it from an overall metric...
呃我们还发现就是呃从一个总体的指标来看
we found that, uh,
会发现呃
Both RAG and AWE saw a significant reduction.
RAG和AWE它都大幅的降低了
Specifically, the utilization failure...
其中的utilization failure
In other words, the failure rate of utilization.
也就是利用的失败率啊
dropping from 24% to around 7%.
从24%降到7%左右啊
But at the same time, the errors for both write and read operations increased.
但是同时呢这个呃write和read的错误都增加了
In contrast, for a strategy like AWI,
作为对比AWI这种策略
its write failure rate,
它的写入的失败率
the write failure remains relatively low.
right failure保一直保持比较低
But its read failure rate is extremely high.
但是它的read failure非常高啊
This might be because it's trying to compress its own information into... uh...
这可能是因为他在把自己信息压缩到呃
in the process of managing its own context,
大模型的自身上下文的过程中
and a lot of important information is lost.
丢失了很多重要的信息
Uh...
呃
What we've found so far is that there isn't a single method,
我们暂时发现是没有一个单一的方法
that can perform well in these three...
能在这三个啊
perform well across the three types of failure rates.
三种失败的失败率上都做的比较好
This trade-off might be one of the fundamental challenges in memory system design.
这可能这个trade off是记忆系统设计中的一个
a rather fundamental challenge.
比较根本性的挑战
Alright, let's wrap things up.
好最后总结是个啊
Take a look.
Take a wa
First of all, on-policy evaluation reveals issues with off-policy...
首先啊on policy的评估揭示了of policy
certain memory-related issues that benchmarks tend to掩盖.
benchmark掩盖的一些记忆方面的问题
If you continue to evaluate memory using static data,
如果你再用静态的数据评估记忆
you're very likely to get some misleading results.
你很可能会得到一些误导性的结果
This is especially true for the evaluation of agents.
特别是针对于agent的评估
The second point is that all current models...
第二点是所有当前的模型啊
Even the most powerful ones,
即使是最强的啊
in long-context conversations,
在长上下文的对话中
all have a significant limitation when it comes to memory.
都有一个显著的啊memory上的局限
It's just superficial fluency.
就是表面的流畅
This might all be masking their actual memory failures.
可能都掩盖了他们啊真实的记忆失败
Third, external memory is helpful.
第三点是额外部的记忆有帮助啊
But it's not perfect, um.
但是并不完美嗯
And we found that among the several types we just mentioned...
并且我们发现在啊刚刚提到的几种啊
failure.
Failure
Writing, reading, and utilization.
Write read realization
And there's a fundamental trade-off among these three types of failures.
这三种failure之间存在一个根本性的trade off
But right now, there isn't a single one.
目前还没有一个啊
method that can effectively solve this problem.
方法能够比较好地解决这个问题
And for the fourth point...
第四点啊
So, self-evolution might be a pretty promising direction.
self evolution可能是一个比较有前景的方向啊
For the agent, we also conducted a pilot study.
agent我们也做了一个pilot study
We found that AASIENT can leverage the feedback from MMGM.
发现AASIENT可以利用m m gm的feedback
to iteratively optimize its own memory strategies.
去迭代优化自身的记忆策略
Right, this is something that might come up in its future self-evolution.
嗯这个点可能会在以后的self evolution中
Yeah, that's a pretty interesting insight, I'd say.
嗯啊是一个嗯比较有趣的insight吧
So, it might use some other mechanisms to iterate on that.
就可能会用一些其他的机制去迭代
to optimize the memory strategies of Agent A itself.
优化A等自身的记忆策略
This could be a potential topic for future work.
这个可以是可能是一个可做的话题
So, to sum it up,
总结来说的话
MMGM is a framework that evaluates the conditional agent memory,
MMGM是实现了对conditional agent memory
a reliable benchmarking diagnostic tool,
的一个可靠的BENCHMARKING诊断
and it also provides potential directions for optimization.
并且提供了一种潜在的优化的可能性的方向
Uh, alright, thank you all for your participation.
嗯啊谢谢大家的这个参与啊
And this is the QR code for our project website.
这个是我们的project website的一个二维码
And of course, feel free to scan this QR code to visit our project page.
然欢迎扫描这个二维码去访问我们的project page哦
Thank you all. Alright.
谢谢大家好的
Thank you, Jiayang.
感谢嘉阳
I was just looking through the comment sections on a few platforms,
我刚才从几个平台的评论区
And also, um, I saw it in our internal group chat.
然后以及嗯我们内部的群里看到了
I have two questions.
有两个问题
Let me help ask the questions.
我来帮忙提问一下
Alright, so the first question is...
首先第一个问题是
So, how does MMGM compare to traditional static benchmarks?
i am gm相比传统静态benchmark
So, what's the fundamental difference in the evaluation approach?
在评审方式上有什么本质的区别
So, what are the advantages of this on-policy evaluation?
这种on policy评测的优势体现在哪里
Well, the most fundamental difference here is that...
额这里的话最核心的一个区别在于呃
The evaluation mode, uh, is basically the mode of evaluation.
evaluation mode就是评估的模式呃
We found that traditional benchmarks,
我们发现传统的benchmark
For example, LOCOMO, NOMEMO, and EMO.
比如说locomo NO man evo啊
They are all 'off-policy' evaluations.
都是这种of policy的评估
In other words, you give the agent a pre-written script for a conversation.
也就是说给A证的写一段啊预先写好的对话
and then ask it a question.
然后问他问题啊
But this approach, uh, doesn't really reflect the agent's own memory capabilities, hmm.
这个其实呃并没有办法反映agent自身记忆能力嗯
So, what's the difference?
的区别啊
Or, to put it another way, if it has a memory deficiency,
或者说如果他有记忆缺陷的话
In fact, it influences the direction of the conversation.
它其实是对对话走向有影响
And this, in turn, will affect the content of its subsequent memory.
而这个又反过来会影响他后续的记忆啊的内容
So, our on-policy...
所以说我们的on policy
So, it solves this issue of coupling.
是解决了这样一个耦合的问题
And then we conduct the evaluation under a more realistic setting.
然后在一个更合理的setting下做的评估
So, the evolution mode is actually the most fundamental difference.
所以其实啊evolution mode是一个最核心的区别啊
And it comes with some other advantages as well.
并且还有一些额外的优势
For instance, uh, our on-policy evaluation...
比如说呃我们的on policy评估
can provide some additional, uh, diagnostic feedback,
可以提供额外的一些呃diagnostic feedback也好
or optimization signals,
或者优化信号也好
This could also potentially guide the improvement of the agent's own memory strategy.
这个可能还可以去指导agent自身记忆策略的改进
optimization.
优化啊
And this is also something that traditional off-policy benchmarks can't do.
这个也是传统of policy benchmark做不到的
So, that's basically the two main points.
大概是这样两点嗯
Alright.
好的
Another question is about the comparison in the experiment with RNG's long context.
还有一个问题是实验中对比了RNG长上下文
the three types of methods: LLMs, agents, and memory.
LLM和agent tic memory3类方法
So, what are the core bottlenecks for each of them?
各自的核心瓶颈是什么
So, when it comes to actual implementation, which one would you choose?
在工程落地时你会怎么选
Right, so for this part, uh...
嗯这块的话额
The core bottlenecks for these three approaches are actually quite clear.
这三类方法的核心瓶颈其实也比较明显啊
First, we have the native VLM.
首先是呃native vlm
we'll find that its bottleneck...
我们会发现它的瓶颈
The real issue is actually with how it utilizes the stored information.
其实是在记忆内容的利用上啊
So, what this means is that even though all the information is right there in its context,
就是说尽管他所有的信息都存在他的context
in its context.
它的上下文里边啊
But its... uh... reading...
但是它的读取的呃
Uh, and this also leads to its... uh... its reading...
呃这也导致它的读取的这个啊
has the lowest failure rate for reading.
failure读取的失败率最低
It doesn't need to retrieve information.
它不需要检索
But as the conversation gets longer,
但随着对话变长啊
it can't effectively search through massive amounts of context
他没有办法在海量上下文中
to effectively use this information.
有效利用这些信息啊
The second point is about RAG.
第二个是这个RAG来说
Its real bottleneck is actually in the write phase.
它的瓶颈其实是在写入这一块
This is because RAG doesn't perform any filtering.
就是因为RAG是不做筛选的
to store the original dialogue.
去存储原始对话
This can lead to some information being lost, hmm.
导致信息可能会存在一定的丢失嗯
The third category.
第三类
In AWE, the 'A' stands for 'autonomous', meaning it decides for itself how to write information.
这个AWE就是A选自自主决定怎么写入信息
Overall, it's actually the most balanced baseline.
它整体其实是最均衡的一个贝斯莱
And we can also see that its...
我们也可以看到他的啊
Its overall score is the best.
总体的得分是最好的
Yeah, that's right.
嗯对
And then, uh, its write failure...
然后呃他的这个write failure
is lower than that of INGD.
是比INGD的呃低的
And then, uh, its read and utilization performance is close to LG's.
然后呃read和utilization又跟LG接近啊
The last category is AWI.
最后一类是AWI
So, for its LM,
就是他的这个LM
writes the content into its own context buffer.
把内容写在他自己的context buffer里面
Uh...
呃
So for this base-fine-tuning approach, the bottleneck is actually in the reading part.
他这种base fine他的瓶颈在在读取部分啊
So, what this means is that it compresses the information into a fixed-size...
就是说他把信息压缩到一个固定大小的
After it's in the in-context buffer,
in context buffer之后啊
This compression process inevitably leads to a loss of detail.
这个压缩过程可能不可避免的损失了细节
And that leads to its... uh...
导致它的啊
has the lowest read failure rate,
red failure最低
But the read failure rate goes up. Yeah, that's about right.
但是read failure变高对大概是啊
Each of them has its own pros and cons.
他们各有这样的一些优优劣
Right, and then, regarding this... for the last small point, which is about practical application...
嗯然后关于这个对最后一个小的就是落地的
So, as for our recommendation...
建议的话啊
Because, all things considered,
因为现在综合来看
So, it seems that AWE still performs the best.
可能啊这个AWE它的性能还是最好啊
So, my advice is, if the conversation isn't too long,
所以说建议如果对话不太长的话
you can just use the native VLLM for its long-context capabilities.
直接用呃native v l i m它的长项长上下文能力
In fact, there's already been a pretty significant improvement.
其实啊已经有了一个比较显著的提升
So you can just use this directly.
可以直接用这个
And when the conversation gets longer,
然后对话比较长的时候
We can use AWE to do it.
可以用AWE去做
Just to add to what this guy said,
对这小子补充